hello
everybody thanks for tuning in
um if you're uh if you've been
watching these videos for a while you're
probably aware i have not been
been posting a few individual videos
just thoughts i've been having
um randomly but i haven't really done
any
uh dialogues with anybody like i was
before
and mostly i've just been doing i've
been really really busy writing this
this uh anthology chapter on dialogos
encircling
um that it'll be published i believe
next summer
as an anthology with a bunch of other
people that
i've talked with on the channel so i've
been putting this on hold
um the channel on hold as i
as i you know attempt to write my first
academically inclined paper i already
have
um two i've i've
i've been given two breaks on getting to
getting to get in by the deadline so
i think this weekend it's the last one
however
i wanted to talk with greg
about this
experience of social fluency and
intelligence
and other kinds of brilliance
and when they don't match up the
complications with that
and what his perspective was on that
especially because greg
he's a psychologist psychotherapist
who's basically
written a unified field theory for
psychology it's very complex and
brilliant and i'm just getting to know
him more in
in in what he calls the tree of
knowledge so it's a it's really quite a
system
so i wanted to um get his perspective on
this and it was a really great
conversation
and uh enjoy uh
announcements we were i think we're just
about full
on the outer circling course but if
if you're interested the links are below
um
you need to act on that quickly because
i think we're i think we're going to cap
it here
um but check it out if you're interested
the links will be below we have every
thursday for circling we have a
an open to the public um event
that's uh six the times change very
recently
six to nine pm um and the link for that
is below
you can sign up through our facebook
channel we also have a brand new website
which is pretty cool and if you if
you're interested in
working with me one-on-one my emails
below and uh
and email me and i can contact with you
and let you know how much it costs and
what it's like
and we can talk all right
enjoy your weekend
there you go welcome back my friend
very nice to be here thanks for having
me you know this is actually going to be
the first video i've done
in a while because i put everything on
pause when i seriously started writing
for the the thing so i'm just right at
they get they extended the deadline a
couple times for me
did you get it in um it's gonna be
in i'll have it turned in by tomorrow so
my first kind of academically inclined
paper which has been really
it's been really interesting but so i i
just put a pause on
on all the videos until i got that done
but gotcha
it's interesting because this is set
this up for people um
you know i think i was i was uh working
with a client
and i was just present to this and it
and i figured i was sitting i was
thinking about it and then i was
thinking about
you in the in your tree of knowledge
right
and all the conversations that we've had
so far and i thought like
i'm just going to shoot him an email
just say like what what is what do you
think about this
and that and then you know and i was as
i was writing that email i was like
actually i have a feeling that this
probably would speak to a lot of
different people
right um and in particularly the thing i
was
the thing i brought up with you was
you know in the i mean i've been working
with i've been working with people
you know in a pretty deep way for like
22 years or so um
you're leading courses and teaching and
doing one-on-one work and working with
families
and so i've noticed i've had a bunch
of clients that i would say
uh
you know a lot of them having i you know
you can almost say like a genius level
iq
right um and
or brilliant in some other kind of way
and and then then i'll start working
with them
and as as we start to kind of like work
through stuff
and usually it has a lot to do with
about their
you know um coaching them around the
relationships
right yep and and as they
as they start to work through their
relationships right
the companies that they're forming and
all those things start to become
successful
but one of the things i've noticed is
that that success
comes is kind of complicated right
because um
because they were so kind of socially
coordinated
right um or socially awkward or socially
you know clumsy um
their relationships with people through
their lives was just filled with like
lots of
like lots of rejection and lots of pain
right however they were bright enough to
kind of know the whole time that they
were right about whatever it was that
they were looking at or they had a
perspective that they could see that was
true
um but but whenever they tried to bring
it out in the world
because whatever is going on with them
socially um
it just wouldn't work out or they get
rejected or people wouldn't pay
attention to them
or all these different kinds of things
so when they start to get successful
and then people start to recognize right
their particular failures it's
on one level it's incredible but
a second later after it comes there's
this experience of
well this has been true the whole time
right right and it it it's complicated
because it comes with
to kind of become successful they have
to kind of work through
this whole world of
of social dynamics right of
relationships that in which they
experience
lots of rejection a lot of rejection
lots of
you know lots of things that come with
you know being socially awkward
right yes and it and it begged you know
and so i wrote wrote you
and the question i had is i just started
to think about
you know if when there does seem to be a
pattern around this
right like that's imagining somewhere
has measured it some somehow
but like this this sense of um
the sense of somebody's somebody can be
incredibly brilliant
but yet it seems like that brilliant
that brilliance
takes all the energy right from
from the social coordination right or
the social sphere
um and
but then but then because they're not
they can't be social they can't make
their relationships work
right um the world ends up missing out
on on their perspective or on their
brilliance
and i and it and it's like um i was
wondering about what is it
about is
you know what is there a way that
evolution and your understanding or in
your map of
your map of um of your tree of knowledge
um does it make sense
is there like an evolutionary reason
right
one that that just happens right um
that this that that somebody really
really with a high iq
or or a genius in some level seems to
can equate a lot of times with you know
a lot of like
social discoordination sure right yes
there's definitely there's a pattern
there and then the other thing is
you know
what is it about right the the thing
about
why does nature select or run
like social um criteria so high
right in a certain sense that you can
actually it actually can miss the
intelligence that's in
that's in it right sure like so just
kind of i wanted to see what your
perspective was
yeah yeah so there's a um
first off i definitely have seen this
clinically i've actually experienced
some of this
i'll be happy to share something about
this yeah um
uh so so let's talk a little bit
about just some of the basic dynamics
here so let's say
you have a kid who's got an iq
of say 145 okay
so and again i don't want to reify the
numbers too much but just
that's somebody who's in the 99th plus
percentile
okay uh and that means that the way they
process information
uh the efficiency with which they
the ease with which they extract out
patterns either verbally
or perceptually okay and then the
creativity with which they might
juxtapose new ideas and start to look at
new
new possibilities operates
significantly outside the norm okay
now if their talents
are aligned with what the edge of what
that
group wants then they can be seen as
geniuses and then realize for that
okay and then you get alignment or
you're like oh my gosh you know you
happen to have a musical
genius we'll say and their talents and
jazz are in classical
and they grow up in a classical and
talents and they're just they're the
great
star uh or they have an athletic ability
and they become the great quarterback
and then everybody sees them and then
they're just
and they have that trajectory and then
they're sort of known and valued for
their unique
talent and and these are the people
we're jealous of in the world
these people look at brad pitt and you
know or whatever imagine
projection of of of of attractiveness of
status
of placement that makes us uh those that
don't feel that
jealous okay so when there's an
alignment then you get
then you see that alignment
but there's many at times not going to
be alignment for a whole host of
different reasons
right so if you have a kid who's 12
and all of a sudden you know let's say
logs on and listens to daniel
schmokenberger you know
okay and can follow what's going on in
relationship to what daniel's saying
and all of a sudden that kid starts to
think wait a minute
because he has the capacity to start
tying stuff together starts getting
worried
about the current state of civilization
right right
all right and starts then tracking this
then he comes back to his friends
okay right and immediately his friends
are
going to be you know his friends are
talking about girls and you know the
latest tick tock thing and who's on
instagram and who's getting likes right
and they're like
what do you you know what is that they
don't have any
frame of reference okay
and if you don't then have a frame of
reference there's a
dunning-kruger effect which is basically
you you can only understand
confidence at your level of confidence
okay
you can't understand you can sort of see
okay that kid's like a smart nerd but i
don't have any clue what he's talking
about
okay and i don't know what
it is that i can uh you know benefit
from that
so it's just outside what the
what the normative structure which is
going to get most of the attention and
social influence
too yep right
um so now the kids got a choice
basically
you know or at least is faced with an un
uh many kids then feel this is sort of
the draw of the interests
or the popularity social engagement
yep yep okay yep um
and and if there and for subset of
people here that will be actually
sort of a hyper androgyny which actually
is a
hyper masculine way of thinking that
tiptoes into
the asd spectrum that's the autistic
disorder spectrum which will be sort of
an analytic
logical way of thinking okay that is
actually uh over emphasizes things like
deductive inductive reasoning
and doesn't pick up on socio-emotional
neurons
yeah okay so now you're gonna
intersect a number of different things
you have something that's really
interested really curious
yeah capable of doing certain kinds of
logic inductive yeah all right
that far out shoots topics than any that
their
peers are interested in and yet at the
same time they
lack a particular type of nuance
or socio-emotional popularity
uh checking in on what's called
relational field dependence which is
like
where's that other person and how much
am i tracking them
yeah okay so so
this creates a very potentially
alienating experience
because the interest in investment is
like wow this is really important stuff
why isn't everybody else see this this
is important
yeah and they don't and at the same time
as you talk about it
the rest of the crew looks to you and
says that we find that you're
you're a weirdo you're you know you're a
nerd you're a geek you're what are you
right right um and
we have you know all of us unless except
for a very unusual
uh disposition or constitution we want
to be known
and valued for what what we our true
self
okay uh and the ideal is when you have a
unique
capacity that you are able to give and
are loved for it
okay yeah and a very confusing thing is
when you feel like you have a unique
capacity
right that you can see is right and then
other people
just find it it actually works against
you
yeah totally that's a that's a
[ __ ] experience right it's like
you know right and so
that's you know that's going to be tough
for people to to metabolize if they
don't have
if they don't have a mentor if they
don't have a deep friend that they can
give voice to and get a narrative that
allows them to hold this emotion
and the social emotional need um what
they're going to do is they'll
compartmentalize it generally they'll
get counter-dependent
okay counter-dependent is i don't eat on
other people right squirrel
okay so after the injury and then the
ineffectiveness and then the isolation
and then the passion
and then you're just sort of like boom
i'm going to cut off this need
to become counter dependent of course
the need really doesn't go away you
basically just pretend
conscious self-consciously that your
subconscious
primal need for belonging and connection
and to be known and valued
you just basically compartmentalize it
and minimize it
yeah yeah okay but that doesn't mean
that you're healthy
does that resonate yeah it does well
it's it's interesting because
you know as you were talking i started
to realize like actually what a lot i
think
a lot of people um
it's because this goes obviously beyond
just my clients because i've seen
you know different people in the bay
area like there's clusters of
people i'm connected with that are just
they're smart beyond belief
right and i started to notice that
there's like a
a re almost a um
what is the what is the word uh like
almost a
uh a sociopathic
strain in them right of where and i
think i
i think i kind of heard the rub of that
of that quality of utter frustration
of here you are and you know you got
something right
but the more you try to present that
around you
um you're not being it's not being seen
it's not being counted for but you know
it's true
but then you're not able to like
it's not able to be recognized right
and then these people are are
liked or whatever or become successful i
there's like a uh
like a
seems like that there's like um a
nihilistic
right a not like a nihilistic
um
deep rage and frustration
i would imagine yes yep right
so you then so think about the dynamics
so you have a
sense that you can see things better
than others okay
you want to be loved for that initially
and then you're rejected
you know in a way that's and you can't
figure out exactly why
right so then you cut off the need to
see
that the need for to be loved out of
actual resentment although you justify
it is by saying you don't need it
but you're also then feeling that you're
superior yep
okay so the dynamic of feeling superior
and already have cut off the need to
have somebody loved is gonna set you up
first basically a narcissistic
debasement of the other
yeah right i mean like i'm just better
than those bastards that gives a [ __ ]
about it
right right doesn't take long to get
into that
you know and then you think you're being
distant but you're actually also
resentful
yeah right that's that's that's the word
resentment the hidden resentful
yes for for not being because the part
of you knows that you'd be so much more
happier and fulfilled if you were being
loved and having the capacity to give
the contribution
right okay right and if you go a long
period
of that and then all of a sudden it
switches right
so then you start becoming successful
right right
and then you start getting pulled into
this yep okay
place all right it's a weird
contrast now all sudden lots of
different things will start to happen
yeah okay to be pulled into this and
will feel very gratifying on the one
hand
yep all right but you're going to say
things like well it's there all along
okay so now what everyone just loves me
because they're following the herd
you know it's a herd mentality it's like
they don't really see it look no one can
see it before now they see it
you know just because i have 6 000 likes
yeah right
yeah and for me i've been working on my
theory forever
20 years from now i'm really famous
everyone wants to talk to me why didn't
you want to talk to me before
yeah and i was just like and
and you already prepared yourself to say
i don't like this i don't need
to like this right unless it's sort of
like
weird and scary and then you have to go
back and say well i was i really hurt
before
right like or am i really going to just
sour this to
maintain my consistency yep yeah
so it's a there's a lot of
socio-emotional
conflict that's this entire trajectory
is going to bring
yeah and unfortunately especially if
you're in a silicon valley thing you
start
you go into the computer engineering and
the algorithmic
right uh ian mcgill chris the master in
his emissary
you know makes a very nice point which
is the
left the logos of the western hemisphere
is really we have given enormous power
to that
so you can be socialized into science
logic out google algorithms that's
what's real
right and and really then you know
be prepared to sort of have a disconnect
between your heart you know heart to
sense the passions who cares about that
yeah actually the real structure is we
should be deploying our logic
to organize our passions not not
controlling and disconnecting them but
but a google world or i'm not dumping on
google but i just mean the silicon
valley world's got a potential
really uh to you know drive that kind of
thinking home
and if it does the alienation from the
relational world from the heart world
the whole
circling attachment world it's very very
important yeah
yeah you said you went through some of
that stuff
yep what like can you share some about
that
yeah sure um you know another thing that
i'll say and certainly this is true for
me
you know the what does it mean to be
smart is a big
deal in our society and you know it's uh
and then to feel like you're smart but
to be not recognized for it
is sets up you know inner conflicts
right yeah so my story you know my
oldest brother my i born into a high
education family both my parents have
the doctorates um
and so you know education
is emphasized um my oldest brother is
valedictorian of a
class of about 800 people so a very high
achiever
my older brother very smart but actively
rebelled against
academics so he didn't do very well but
it was seen
as very as charismatic and charming and
quick on his feet and all of that
and i had a bit of a learning disability
i was not a good reader
yeah so i'd swap my b's and d's
um and not being a good reader uh
made my academic achievement through
elementary and uh
medical middle school not that great and
i didn't find it to be very meaningful
yeah yeah kinds of stuff i was
intuitively drawn to
um and all of that made
my father who had a and i'm very close
to my dad but this isn't we
processed this this is a big was an
issue over time
my father had a fixed uh attribute
theory of intelligence
fixed attribute means that you're this
is the idea that you're born with a
particular
you know we could pull that out of you
somehow and measure it and you're like
oh okay my dad would that guy's
unbelievably smart that guy's pretty
smart that guy's average
and then once you fall into my dad's
category yeah then then you're basically
tattooed with that
category okay um and actually in the
world of
psychology you may have heard the
difference between fixed and growth
mindsets
like a growth mindset is when you really
are helping people realize not that
intelligence
is very easily thought of as you know as
a learning
structure developmental thing if you
don't get something right it's because
you can learn and do something
more that you learn from your mistakes
as opposed to well that's diagnostic of
whether or not what your
you know innate ability is right right
different people have different frames
of what intelligence is
there's certainly some truth to both of
them in some ways but uh different
people did so anyway my father
was one of those people who would see uh
sort of in a conservative established
way whoever were the absolute
experts that who intended to defer to
them and grant them
status okay um and i'm i was then placed
as
you know not very bright right my father
right and i didn't in my heist
up into my middle and high school years
that basically was part of my identity
that was not
i didn't struggle with that yeah okay i
was sort of uh
you know i i was uh kind of a get along
go along
you know pretty easy type you know
stereotype of what's a b
type b personalities like hey you know i
don't need to achieve um
you know i don't have super high
conscientiousness to trait levels and
i'm an easygoing guy kind of deal right
right um
but it's also the case that i was a it
turns out that i was a late bloomer and
the way i bloomed was really kind of
unique
you know and then the blooming of that i
was a late bloomer and the way i bloomed
was you know kind of unique and uh
and weirdly weirdly unique yeah really
quite frankly at least from a first
person perspective i mean you go around
and say well yeah i built a unified
theory of knowledge
okay that's a that's a weird thing to
believe you know i was like i've solved
some of the hardest problems in the
history of mankind
and and i do believe that and it's weird
though right
um so so especially to have a professor
father
okay so um so went through a whole
process
i remember so what happened in
underground is i started to bloom and
undergraduate
and i um i taught myself basically i
read enough so that then i could
actually read
and then read with efficiency and then
when i
um could read uh that helped
reading help yeah like now you can
actually all right
you know and then when i sort of
overcome whatever dyslexia i had then i
could be
and i had a great mentor who's actually
still uh he's on the tok executive
committee he
was he's only 10 years older than i've
been he was a new uh
doctoral uh abd professor in sociology
and
uh you know introduced me to theory and
i took some feminism classes
and i just woke up and then
whatever my schematic system was a
sponge
for it's essentially it's a social
science coherence
capacity that i have i can just just
basically absorb social science theory
with an enormous amount of ease it does
it takes me an abstract to read
something and i was like oh i know what
that person's saying i don't need to
read the rest of it
um
easy to read social science theory
you can get it like that because what
can you summarize basically what is it
about a social science theory
that is um rockable enough is it is it
that
is it is just is it is it is it is it
presented in a particular way
like you know like math is presented
often in numbers and formulas is
what's the thing that you're grocking
actually
um it's a good question i have a very
intuitive uh understand
analytic intuitive understanding of the
socio-emotional processes of human
beings
yeah yeah yeah so
sort of like you know it's like some
people understand computers really well
it's like
i just i just know how people work right
yeah now that part would you say
would you say that has been online in a
way that was interesting to you
like through your whole life and then it
just academically blossomed later in
life
yeah yeah the the so i knew i wanted to
be a psychologist because i could talk
to
people really easy and immediately
empathize where everyone was coming from
so like in my family when i was 10 you
know people would be coming to me and i
could understand dad thinks this and mom
thinks this and my brother thinks this
and this is why we all get it wrong this
way and the best thing we should do is
this
right right so that that intuitive
capacity to empathize with people is
always precious yeah um it wasn't really
recognized as a real
intellectual skill it was just it was
just present and as my mom
would say will you be the glue of the
family you know everyone comes and
checks in with you and gets
sort of easily mirrored by you is it is
it is that actually recognized as an
intellectual school skill now well it
depends on who you talk to but certainly
like if you go into the multiple
intelligences world of howard gardner
he talks about both personal and social
intelligences yeah okay so it would
it would fall into that category of
of being able to be aware of self aware
of others
intuitively track you know there's this
social dynamics
yeah like i i it just
all the little nuances of people's
facial expressions their gestures their
tones of voice
that just pops for me in relationship to
their affective positioning
yeah yeah so you know that's
so like literally and you can read a
person's
affective positioning in some way that
i'm sure it's almost
impossible for you to explain how you do
it it's more like you just
it's you just kind of show you just sort
of like that you know it's like
and then i'll ask my students i'll be
like well what do you see what's going
on there and they're like
well the person i i don't know they're
just talking about this thing it's like
no they're saying this and then they had
this insecurity and then they
compensated for this way and then they
said this and then they were defended
against this right
they're like what yeah and i was like i
mean you know that's pretty obvious
here's
the thing and like yeah totally
isn't that what's going on it's like i
just thought they were just telling this
story
yeah yeah but if you listen to the
juxtaposition bouncing of why did they
justify this and then they did this and
then they told this story and then
look at their facial expression so you
know it's just
right we all that's part of the
intelligence is to have certain schemes
that's really good at pattern detection
yeah and that was happened to be mine
and the
combination of that and not being able
to be read and being in a
family where intelligence was really uh
overly assessed in terms of
you know academic achievement right
confused in that way that
happened and then when i overcame my
academic limitation
and then also realized that you know
hey i can now understand this domain of
academia in a particular way so i can
i can read feminist theory and
instantaneously be like oh my gosh yes
white men do this and then they justify
it this way and then they're gonna
dictate power and i do that oh my god
now i really you know a couple of
articles of feminism and now it's like
i'm
you know the power structures in fact i
even brought it home and we
had a you know my mom was going through
some transitions anyway
it was important in our family because
we were i had three other brothers and
we were definitely male dominated and my
dad was
um you know we said we were more
egalitarian than we were that's for sure
yeah and this opened my eyes to it yeah
but in terms of what
there was an evolution that happened to
me from say 19 right
to 27 28 right
where the i essentially went through a
whole nother
layer of developmental education
and shot into a series of steps that
took me thinking about the world
yeah um and and an evolutionary stage
model
you know if you want to do an integral
thing and start climbing up the
developmental stages right and
um you know was quickly you know so i
jumped into green
postmodern with feminism you know and
then started
seeing critical theory and quickly
evolved out of my modernist perspective
yeah and then by you know
93 i was then in my master's degree i
quickly
was interested in psychotherapy
integration so i was then quickly drawn
into a more integral
place and yeah and just was
intuitively convinced that there are
needs that each one of these things is
playing an instrument
and there is an overall music to this
uh to the to the cosmos here and
i'm on my you know i'm just drawn
to ask questions to try to elucidate
that yeah so so that's kind of the
journey at the level the ego dynamic
there's a that's a whole nother
layer i'd be happy to share but that's
that's that's the
sort of the intellectual awakening took
that yeah
trajectory yeah huh
it's interesting i don't think that
people think about empathy
it's interesting thinking about that
like because i didn't
i wouldn't have thought that empathy was
a
was about a kind of intelligence i would
have thought about it as
an emotional thing until it was time to
teach
people how to circle and then i realized
that no there are all these things that
i'm perceiving
that i put together that are happening
kind of in an instant
right and it's as i'm trying to explain
this back
or describe it which is not easy to do
right that's a whole
exercise of an intelligent that is like
does not come easy
um but yeah i was like oh there no this
is there's a whole
in order to get where you're coming from
it isn't just
you have feelings over there that i pick
up on and feel them with you
and it's like there's a empathy is being
able to grok
the way the world's coming at you why
it's coming at you that way
like what you think what you're probably
thinking about that person
and how you what you think about them
and and then therefore the world and
time and it's like it look like all of
these
dynamical distinctions come into
somebody's
experience right right right
and what's interesting to me as i'm
curious about for you
like with this one is
there is an emotional component though
around it if there's a
reason like there's a reading component
of their emotions and being able to get
the meaningfulness of their emotions
um and what all that presupposes
but then there's the process of of
being in relationship to it it's not it
it is one of feeling i find it's one of
like
empathy is one where you get their
position and that you have this
experience for me it's like this
experience of like of course
like it like the world makes sense
understanding you
it's like right you feel relief in that
and that you make sense to me right
and there's a mutual like there's
something about a heartful intelligence
that seems to be really close to the
cognitive part of that
definitely definitely i mean for me so
and if i go into the unified theory
language of this okay
uh this is your intuitive influence
matrix
right okay yeah immediately places the
person
in this socio-emotional self-other world
right in both the here and now and the
developmental
trajectory of it okay yeah so it's just
like
what is the social sphere of influence
and the developmental history of the
matrix of
social and emotional experiences right
right
right that that heart intuitive system
has
and how does it connect to how they're
narrating into themselves into me right
now
yeah yeah yeah and for whatever reason
my architecture just had that online
that was like you know i could just sort
of like boom and i could take mine and
then i can jump into your matrix
yeah yeah yeah and be like oh
absolutely yes if you had this and this
was your mom and this was your dad and
that's the context in which you were and
this was the way
you were traumatized by this event
that's how you thought about it now we
bring it through the developmental
trajectory of course you'd be feeling
right now these conflicts right
right and uh yeah that's a
particular kind of ability slash
intelligence
absolutely you know it's a reasonable
term to use
yeah intuitive and by intuitive
what makes it intuitive what like what
is your definition of intuitive in that
sense
well intuitive in that sense would
basically be the
more it's it's not necessarily i mean
now i can actually give
logos analysis to it
um but a lot would be normally the issue
is just the ability to do it
okay sort of like in other words and
then you ask them propositionally
like how do you do that and you're like
well i mean isn't it obvious
right it's like no because if we had
somebody on the spectrum here who asked
these questions the person would be
completely clueless
yeah about what the other person was
feeling right i mean that would be
so that's the big ability difference
yeah uh
i mean that's one of the defining
features of just descriptively of
individuals
on the spectrum is that they have
significant blind spots
uh simon baron cohen called it mind
blindness
yeah which they don't it's very hard for
them
to jump in into this intuitive
empathetic
mode for somebody else and see the world
through the other person's
uh experience so they just don't have
the quite the architecture
yeah and and that's perspectival and
participatory knowing
to use john some john terms you know
which means that your self-conscious
ability to actually know exactly what
you're doing
you know is hard it's more like can you
ride the bike you know you get on the
bike and you ride it you know that's
procedural knowing
um how do you do that i don't know i
pedal i
just kind of it comes you know it seems
like it's easy or
it's not you know but then everything
else is just sort of a weak
description of it yeah so that's what i
intuitive would be more
there's non-verbal just display of skill
or the absence of skill yeah that would
then be
just you know people trying to post-hoc
rationalize what's going on but usually
if you listen carefully they
they don't offer rich descriptions
right right
so the pop the part about
i mean is there is there do you know is
there an evolutionary
reason that you
understand if it's even fair if you can
put it like this but like
that you would that nature
or genes or evolution would select
for um this
we could say extreme intelligence
and then over over the social
coordination
right
why why often times there's that that
there's that
imbalance and it seems i think it's i
i don't know and this may be because i
just live in the bay area and
there's more and more people that come
here that are
super super super smart because of the
tech industry but
but my understanding is like like uh
people on the spectrum is like
20 times more than it's been in like the
last 20 years than it was
right so right so
there's a whole host of right there's a
whole host of issues here yeah
i'm not sure i put it i mean
you know we get into the there's there's
the basic frequency distribution of
talent
yeah um so any cluster of talent is
going to have a normal distribution
yep all right and it probably is the
case that if you go
i think it's reasonable i don't really
like mar uh howard gardner uses multiple
intelligences
i think that gets a little confusing but
believe me there are definitely
multiple clusters of ability sets yeah
okay
multiple clusters of ability sets and
actually those ability sets at a general
level there is a general positive
weak positive correlation through all of
them there actually is a constitutional
functionality
okay so if i know you have 140 iq at the
verbal analytic level yeah chances are
you may
you will be above average on your social
emotional ability
right correlationally so they will
but you know that's a huge difference if
i'm
looking at you and saying wow look at
how unbelievably smart you are in this
domain
but you have the equivalent of a 105 iq
at the socioemotional intelligence
you're going to get a contrast effect
you're going to be like that guy's
really brilliant over here
right you know okay um and quite frankly
what you're gonna see often
there are some sex differences here okay
so you're gonna see
say really high the more common pattern
then
as a high iq male who has
instrumental intelligence that allows
them to you know
engage in computer engineering and solve
algorithms
and then have a very intelligent wife
but the distribution of her intelligence
is going to be a lot more
likely to be in the socio-emotional um
access to relational dynamics yeah
yeah so then what you see then is you
know a rich intelligent
woman saying why does my very very smart
husband
seem so underdeveloped in his capacity
to attend to these ruling nuance for
relational dynamics and tell me how he
feels
yeah yeah he's like what are you talking
about
all right here we are you know that's
what we're talking about
yes exactly so
yeah so so there are these different
distributions
of of intelligence that will weakly
correlate
i i certainly think then there's the
other issue about whether
whether our diet our lifestyle the
technological world that we live in
are breeding us to you know develop
certain kinds of intellectual abilities
and greatly under develop
uh some of the socio-emotional abilities
there are lots of good reasons
um i mean think about what we used to
live in hunter-gatherer bands
everything is deep rich relation
with oral narrative negotiation in a
group setting where everybody knows
everybody over time
deeply well you're related or deep
friends
engaged in you know serious life and
death
activity together and you all have to
depend upon each other yeah
that the network of relational harmony
versus sitting in your room looking at
instagram trying to get likes
solving math problems right it's just a
radically different environment for
really impoverished environment for many
kids into adults
that don't afford the ongoing
development of this nuanced relational
matrix
embedded in real oral indigenous
relational
processes over time so i think that
there's good reason
to think that we have created a society
uh that's going to give rise to
you know people who are impaired in
their
richness of their capacity for uh
sophisticated relating right totally
i just and i think we're i think it's
happening at such a rate
i mean it's literally happening at such
an exponential
rate that i don't even think we're aware
that we're doing a huge experiment
you know right everyone needs to be
aware this is an unbelievable
i mean every generation is
has has accelerated the difference from
where we used to live
farther and farther yeah and you know
evolutionary psychologists call this
mismatch the mismatch of the evolved
environment that we're prepared for from
the environment that we're born into
right and this was acceleratingly
different
you know in the 1950s this was
unbelievably different and now with
digital
i mean the digital is taking the
difference
and just putting on steroids and so
um that's why you know we're at the from
a tok perspective we're at the fifth
joint point
we need everyone to wake up because the
danger of change
and of rapid change so dramatic change
and then being so alienated from our
natures i mean it's already going to
happen
in a devastating way but we have to work
super hard
to keep it from spiraling out of control
you
really need we need people who can
bridge
that and know what the heart needs and
we need to figure out how to have social
relations
yeah you know circling and experiences
to the heart gets
nervous right exactly yeah i think
that's why
you know we've talked about this before
too but that's one of the reasons why
where why i think circling even even
how it ended up spreading right on so
many different levels everywhere
it's it's on one level it says something
about the methodology
but it also and then i think even more
says more about the time we're in
that people are starting well i think
you would have had a hard time selling
that to 100
they would have been like what are you
talking about yeah i mean we sit around
talking to each other all the time
[Laughter]
private wood spaces they can at least
get away from some of the immersion
that's what that's what it sold back
then
but here no doubt it's it's the the
heart is undernourished
at the relational level circling is such
a you know gets
right to the authentic connection then
people feel it and they
they've intuitively known that they
haven't had that
fed but then when it's fed it's like oh
my god you know what have we been
missing
yeah totally and it does seem like
it does seem like well one i've noticed
that that there is an experiment when
people have that experience
they know there's a that that they could
make that's
possible right and that just having a
new horizon open up that feels like
a memory that you've never had right
like they've never had it but they
remember like oh this
it's almost like oh where have i been my
whole life i remember
you that never happened yeah yeah that's
because we have eyes and that will
reorganize
things right because the at least from
an influence matrix
uh perspective which says you carry that
unconscious memory and that's good
evolutionary sense you have
templates for understanding what it is
to be known and valued
yeah and and then if you're not you deny
them and pretend like it's not
but then when it comes flooding in right
it's an archetypal experience it is like
oh my gosh this is what it's like to be
known and valued
and the entire body responds right
okay because because yeah it really is
like a memory
of what it is like to be loved over the
generations we have that we're ready to
see that and if you haven't seen it and
then all of a sudden you feel it the
entire
system gets recalculated and organized
definitely
totally and it's it's an un and it's
and you can't argue with it when
somebody's experienced
it's like it's like it's almost like uh
it's
synonymous with with i don't know a
spiritual experience that you have to
experience but that but
you realize that you're there's a sense
in which oh my god my
nervous system is designed
it just dab and all we did we sat across
from each other and
we made sounds right
[Laughter]
in a relatively rhythmic way and
this my whole world view looks different
and i think
i was going to ask you about this too
because i was uh
you know as i'm writing this a lot of a
lot of what my section is about
is is more than i was imagining it was
going to be about is about the sense of
techn
about the running away sense of
technology right
and as a you know as
as a pretext for you know looking at
circling and
the logo so now goes into the logos well
like well why does it even make sense
and so i actually ended up going through
heidegger's whole notion of of that
because he was so
he saw it at such a deep level um
and and i was i
so i've been really reminded of this
sense in which
this you know as things acceler
accelerate more and more
and become more technological and the
more convenient and the more
streamlined it's interesting because
in the economies mirroring this it seems
like the basic feedback loop of
of general intelligence right um
is rewarded immensely in
in the economy in all these ways problem
solving consciousness
right but it's
however it's and this is why i'm
wondering about like in terms of
the wisdom right and wisdom is distinct
from
intelligence in the in the strict sense
of the word right
like my wisdom is the thing
that has you know what to be intelli
what
like the goals upon which you would have
the problems that you would then solve
at this point we're just
solving problems and there's a default
you know it's gotten to the point where
it's gotten so fast where
we're solving problems that we don't
have
called and they're turning into like
faster phones
like more technology where it's obvious
there's no need for it right no one's
even asking for it but yet the
atmosphere is asking for it right a
momentum of its own
it's almost like we're solving a problem
and the problem
ends up being everything is turned into
something as a
resource to collapse distances to become
technological so you have this end
this cycle of everything is contingent
a a contingency for something else and
that something else is actually already
contingency for something else
and you have all this but there's no
sense of like
wisdom like yoda in the back like like
oh we're gonna die
like go for luke right i mean there's a
i think that virtually all the wisdom
traditions yeah
help us to reflect on the difference
between
instrumental doing and being yeah
right and and the difference between you
know
means to ends and ultimate ends yeah you
know you do to aristotle
you know it's very clear about what's
the ultimate end then everything else is
an instrument but we shouldn't be clear
about what the ultimate end is
yeah and you know you never you never
treat another individual
instrumentally they are an end of
themselves right
what is fundamental virtue how do we be
be wary of doing you know i mean you
have to do sometimes but obviously
you know especially the eastern
traditions right so we think about each
one of those wisdom traditions now we
look at the
you know the capital economy you know
the capital economy fundamentally is
about instrumental act
doing to acquire more [ __ ] and consume
more [ __ ]
so that you climb up some mark indirect
marker rank
and have more [ __ ] than the next guy
right totally
you know and and so how do we
efficiently get more [ __ ]
is essentially where all the
contingencies wrapped up into
so everything is instrumental doing i'm
going to use you for instrumental i'm
going to market myself to be
instrumental
i'm going to have everything to then
acquire some need
and then and it has an atheistic
scientific backdrop of mechanism
and and all of that is is exactly the
you know you try to do that you climb
that up and then you real you know why
you have
mid middle uh midlife crisis and now we
don't even need to wait for midlife it's
just
happening in adolescence you're like you
know i'm stressed
i'm pressured i don't even know what the
hell i'm doing yeah
you know what am i doing this really for
yeah um
and that i think this is part of the
meeting crisis of course that john talks
about so
profoundly the acute modern mean crisis
is so many people are both
you know realizing these are empty
calories and realizing
despite all the stuff we have we feel
so alienated or so many people feel so
alien right and so hungry
for something else and that's one of our
great challenges
is where we built a titanic that's great
at chewing up
the oceans and turning them into stuff
but you know the earth can't take it and
quite frankly we don't need it where do
we we we've
solved the material problems we need to
get back to solving
the wisdom problems and relational
problems right
it's it's it's now sit around and talk
and learn and
sing and dance and embody you know our
process but i mean that's not where our
values our philosophies our
wisdom is so hopefully we can awaken to
yeah totally and there's something about
i think that there's something about you
know as we're talking i'm
it's clicking it's clicking in for me
even even more about
the one thing that i don't think that
you can optimize
right is real intimacy i think it's like
it's interesting because i was
because by if you just do the numbers
i mean odds are we're gonna be
we're gonna turn into machines and it'll
occur
it'll occur like our idea like as a good
thing and we'll
we'll turn into machines and we'll give
up all of it
and we'll not it will will not have even
even been noticed
right or something like that right
there's certainly a trans human fear
hope
weird thing that is that yes and
obviously yeah the uh
i don't know if you saw like a elon musk
you know release neural link
um which you know getting closer and
closer plugging stuff in and
once you get that interface you know
yeah so anyway yep
yep that's happening it's so interesting
but the but the uh
it seems to me though that
there's one place like the one place and
i'm sure there's other places but
there's a there's a there's a feedback
loop in
inner subjectivity right that
to really listen to somebody right as an
end in themselves as a vow right you
actually can't you you
you can't do that you actually have to
do it
right like you actually have to
not be instrumental like you actually
have to slow down and
have that experience right so there is a
there is a sense in which i think it's
one of the i think
you're right i think inner subjectivity
is the one
is the place that it's on some level
it's going to be our saving grace
right because it has to be yeah right
because it's
and i think how it's going to save us is
that i don't think that technology can
can handle the pain of that missing
right it is missing
and it is hurting people and on some
level
we're able to get enough shiny objects
right
to to not notice the meaninglessness
yep but i think that our being
can't do it right it can't do that
ultimately and i think our saving graces
it
is that the technology isn't going to be
to be able to address that pain and i
think that pain
is where the wisdom is going to be right
yep i think that's where it's going to
be i agree with that i agree with all of
that i mean i i think that
uh you know
the the the core of our embodied being
is centered around for me centered
around experience of relational value
so we are we're uh you know we're born
and all of a sudden we look up and we're
tracking
our mother's eyes you know and we are
looking to see
that dance immediately that mirrored
attachment contextual dance
you know sets the stage you know
and and then we're hunting for whether
or not we are known and valued
uh you know have influenced and are
valued and that's those are two
different things and we can
use influence and then mat and then or
not or we're injured and rejected
yeah and you know i mean
i just put up on the list tom friedman
you know talking about
you know what is the core from his
analysis about what's going on
dignity humiliation you know what's
everybody everybody's
fighting to humiliate the other and
claim dignity
and you know what are these things these
are the fundamental
structures uh that that really
feed our embodied sense of of meaning
and so yeah that the fear is that we've
lost so much touch with it and created
systems that break that apart and gave
rise to
but um you know i love dialogos i
love circling i love the idea that we're
in the process of exploring
psycho technologies that could use zoom
and use communities to bring people
together
um and realize that we have enough
material stuff taken care of and now
we got to get back to the soul you know
we got to get back to the
embodied uh connection with each other
right in the world right totally
all right my friend i'm gonna i'm gonna
go ahead and complete
time for me to go right again all right
well good luck
you know i'm glad that welcome to the
academy
yeah totally fun fun huh
yeah great talking with you thanks sir
this is really great always good talking
hey man
enjoy it a lot let's do it again some
time ago okay
bye peace